<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English farrier, or, Countrey-mans treasure Shewing approved remedies to cure all diseases, hurts, maimes, maladies, and griefes in horses: and how to know the severall diseases that breed in them; with a description of every veine; how, and when to let them blood, according to the nature of their diseases. With directions to know the severall ages of them. Faithfully set forth according to art and approved experiment, for the benefit of gentlemen, farmers, inholders, husbandmen, and generall for all.</title>
            <title>Verie perfect discourse, and order how to know the age of a horse, and the diseases that breede in him, with the remedies to cure the same</title>
            <author>L. W. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109988</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845614</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 956:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English farrier, or, Countrey-mans treasure Shewing approved remedies to cure all diseases, hurts, maimes, maladies, and griefes in horses: and how to know the severall diseases that breed in them; with a description of every veine; how, and when to let them blood, according to the nature of their diseases. With directions to know the severall ages of them. Faithfully set forth according to art and approved experiment, for the benefit of gentlemen, farmers, inholders, husbandmen, and generall for all.</title>
                  <title>Verie perfect discourse, and order how to know the age of a horse, and the diseases that breede in him, with the remedies to cure the same</title>
                  <author>L. W. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 4 leaves, 5-41, [3] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Beale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An expanded anonymous reprint of: C., L.W.  A verie perfect discourse, and order how to know the age of a horse, and the diseases that breede in him, with the remedies to cure the same.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf bear the same woodcut of a horse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The English farrier, or, Remedies for curing of diseases in horses.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horses --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Horses --  Age --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of the veins of a horse</figDesc>
                  <head>I B</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>The 2 temple v</item>
                        <item>The 2 eye. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 forhead. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 pallet. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 necke. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 plate. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 fore ſhanke. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 ſide. ve</item>
                        <item>The ſhanke. ve</item>
                        <item>The houfe. v</item>
                        <item>The hanch. ve</item>
                        <item>The taile. ve</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure> 
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a farrier's tools</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Engliſh Farrier, OR, Countrey-mans Treaſure. Shewing approved Remedies to cure all Diſeaſes, Hurts, Maimes, Maladies, and Griefes in Horſes: and how to know the ſeverall Diſeaſes that breed in them; with a deſcription of every Veine; how, and when to let them blood, according to the nature of their Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With directions to know the ſeverall Ages of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully ſet forth according to Art and approved ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, for the benefit of Gentlemen, Farmers, Inholders, Husbandmen, and generally for all.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the farrier's profession</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>At London printed by <hi>John Beale</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:3"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> How and when a horſe ſhould be let blood, &amp; by what ſigne a man may know whether it bee needfull or no.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> In how many Veines a horſe may be let blood, with a deſcription of the ſeverall Veines.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> Directions to know when to let a Horſe blood, and in what Veine, and for what diſeaſe, griefe, or cauſe, and how to know the griefe or diſeaſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> How to know the Age of a Horſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> Things neceſſary to be knowne by every Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> To know the ſeverall Diſeaſes that grow in Horſes and in what parts they grow, and upon what cauſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 7.</label> How to judge of the ſickneſſes and impediments in a horſe by his Doung or Ordure.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8.</label> How to judge of the ſickneſſes or impediments in a Horſe by his Stale or Vrine.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9.</label> A deſcription of the number, qualities, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Sinews of a Horſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 10.</label> Of the three powers or vertues whereby as well the body of a Horſe as every other beaſt is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 11.</label> Of the number and ſituation of bones that be in a Horſes body.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 12.</label> In what points the art of ſhooing doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and of hooves and of the divers kinds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 13.</label> Of paring and ſhooing the perfect hoove<pb facs="tcp:10523:4"/>and fore-feete, and how to make the ſhooes and nayles.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 14.</label> Of paring and ſhooing the hinder feet.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 15.</label> How to keepe the hoove of a horſe moyſt in the Stable, and the Receit of the oyntment.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 16.</label> Approved Remedies for curing all kindes of Diſeaſes, Hurts, Maymes, Maladies or Griefes, in Horſes.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:4"/>THE Engliſh Farrier, OR Countrey-mans Treaſure.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 1. How, and when a horſe ſhould be let blood, and by what ſigne a man may know whether it be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or no.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, to preſerue health, it is good to let him blood foure times a yeere</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the Sprng about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnng of May, becauſe the blood beginneth to increaſe: Secondly, in Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, becauſe the blood beng then inflamed ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually, may euaporate or breake out: Thirdly, about the middeſt of December, to let out the groſſe and knotty blood: Fourthly, about the middeſt of March.</p>
            <p>But I would not wiſh you to let a horſe blood but once a yeare, &amp; that in the beginning of May, within a fortnight after his putting to graſſe; for then you ſhall let out the groſſe and old blood, and the new will come in his place: Except it be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on great need, I would wiſh you not to let him blood at all: for oft letting blood cauſeth debility in the horſe, it hindreth the ſight, and maketh the blood reſort inwardly, which cloyeth the heart and intrals, and leaueth the outward parts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:5"/>
            <head>Chap. 2. In how many Veines a horſe may be let blood, with a deſcription of the ſeverall Veines.</head>
            <list>
               <item>IN the two Temple Veines, which bee the firſt and principall Veines in the head.</item>
               <item>In the two Eye veines, which are eaſie to find in the face of the horſe, ſomewhat beneath his eies</item>
               <item>In the two Pallet veines in the Mouth.</item>
               <item>In the two Necke veines.</item>
               <item>In the two Plate veines which are in the breaſt.</item>
               <item>In the two Fore-head veines.</item>
               <item>In the two Fore-ſhanke veines.</item>
               <item>In the two Fore veines before.</item>
               <item>In the two Side veines, which may be called the Shanke veines.</item>
               <item>In the Taile-veine.</item>
               <item>In the Hanch-veine.</item>
               <item>In the Hoofe-veine.</item>
               <item>In the two Fore ſhanke veines behind.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So that an horſe may be let blood in 13 veins: All which, are eaſie enough to know, becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one lyeth in a little Gutter, which you ſhall find by feeling with your finger.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to know when to let a horſe blood, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what Veine, and for what diſeaſe, griefe, or
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and how to know the griefe or diſeaſe.</head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>diagram of the veins of a horse</figDesc>
               <head>I B</head>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The 2 temple v</item>
                     <item>The 2 eye. v</item>
                     <item>The 2 forhead. v</item>
                     <item>The 2 pallet. v</item>
                     <item>The 2 necke. ve</item>
                     <item>The 2 plate. ve</item>
                     <item>The 2 fore ſhanke. ve</item>
                     <item>The 2 ſide. ve</item>
                     <item>The ſhanke. ve</item>
                     <item>The houfe. v</item>
                     <item>The hanch. ve</item>
                     <item>The taile. ve</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>If his eies be watriſh, or bloud-ſhotten or grieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Pin or web, or haw, then it is good to let him blood in the Eye veine, with a fleme.</p>
            <p>If he haue any wearineſſe or heauines of body, or be diſeaſed in the throat with the ſtranglings or Quinaſie, or ſwelling of the Arteries either within or without, then it is good to let him blood in the Pallat veines in the mouth with a Cornet.</p>
            <p>If he be vexed with an Ague, or with any other diſeaſe vniuerſall hurting his Body, then let him blood in the Necke-veine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>If his griefe be in the Lungs Liuer, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inward part: then let him bloud in the breſt veines, which we call (before) the Plate veines.</p>
            <p>If he be grieued in the ſhoulders, then let him blood in the fore-féete veines aboue the knee with a launce, and that very warily: for that place is full of Sinewes.</p>
            <p>If hee be grieued in the Ioynts, then let him blood in the Shackle-veines, and that very wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: for that place is full of Sinewes alſo.</p>
            <p>If he be foiled in the fore-feet with Foundring, or otherwiſe, then let him blood in the two veins (make way firſt with your drawer, to come to your veines) in the Fore-feete.</p>
            <p>If he be diſeaſed in the Kidnies or Reines, Backe or Belly then let him blood in the Flank-veines.</p>
            <p>If he haue any griefe in his hips, then let him<pb facs="tcp:10523:6"/>blood in the taile vaine, or hoofe veine.</p>
            <p>If his hinder Legges be grieued, or Ioynts, or Feete: then let him blood on the <hi>Shackle-Veins,</hi> and on the two veines behind on the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Feete,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 4. How to know the age of a Horſe.</head>
            <p>A Horſe hath forty teeth: the thirtieth moneth after his foaling he looſeth two aboue and two beneath; in the fourth yeere, he looſeth two aboue and two beneath: when he is fiue, he caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the reſt both aboue &amp; beneath. Thoſe that come firſt aboue, are hollow: when he is ſix, his hollow teeth are filled vp: and in the ſeuenth all the reſt are filled vp: then you may no longer iudge of his age by his teeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 5. Things neceſſary to be knowne by every Far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ier.</head>
            <p>AS firſt to know into what diſeaſe a horſe is inclinable.</p>
            <p>Secondly what be the cauſes of euery diſeaſe in particuiar,</p>
            <p>Thirdly how and by what w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes and meanes theſe diſeaſes doe grow.</p>
            <p>Fourthly the ſignes how to know and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them,</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſty the meanes and mannr how to cure them,</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:7"/>
            <head>Chap. 6. To know the ſeverall diſeaſes that grow in horſes, and in what parts they grow, and upon what cauſes.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>BAgges,</hi> in the weakes of the mouth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barbs,</hi> be two teats growing vnder the tong.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bottes,</hi> doe grow and breed in the Maw &amp; guts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bliſters,</hi> on his body, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth through heat &amp; cold.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Canker,</hi> is in his mouth venomed, &amp; wil make his tong to haue clifts, and ſcabs in his vpper lips vnderneath, and are full of black a weales or pimples, ſo that he can hardly eate his meate.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coult-Evill,</hi> is by ranknes of water and bloud: it will cauſe his belly and Yeard to ſwell.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cloying,</hi> is in the hoofe of the Feete.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cords,</hi> is a ſtacke ſinew in the legges before.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bs,</hi> is a ſwelling ſinew behinde the hoofe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crotches,</hi> is a ruffe ſcuruines about the fetlocks</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Interfeering,</hi> is ſtriking on the ioynt aboue the paſtorne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farcion,</hi> or <hi>Farcie,</hi> is a Scabbe or knobs brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in diuers places of his body, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth chiefely in the Veines.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Feaver,</hi> is a ſickeneſſe taken with cold, and will cauſe him to ſhake.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thiſtula,</hi> is an old rotten Sore in the body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Foundering,</hi> is taken in the body, and feet alſo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fraying,</hi> is taken in the body, feet, and legges, which is a ſtiffeneſſe comming only with cold.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Prounce</hi> or <hi>Pimples,</hi> is in the pallet of his mouth, Galling, or other hurt: and come eſpecially by eating of frozen graſſe, or duſt.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gigges</hi> or <hi>Flapes,</hi> are Pimples or Teats in the inſide of the mouth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glaunders,</hi> are Curnels vnder his Iawes: and when they are ripe, they will run at his Noſe, and ſo breake out.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gorge,</hi> is a ſwelling of bloud on the legges</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gravelling,</hi> is taken in the Feet</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Web</hi> in the Eye, or the <hi>Haw,</hi> which is a Griſtle growing on the Feime which ſcowreth the Eye</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hide</hi> bound, is when the ſkinne cleaueth to the fleſh and the Ribbes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hoofe-bound,</hi> is in the pinching of the hoofe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Itch in the Tayle,</hi> is by exceſſe of blood.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lampas,</hi> is the fleſh in the mouth nigh the vpper Teeth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mange,</hi> is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mallender,</hi> is a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the knees.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Molt-long,</hi> is the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>-hoofe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mourning of the Chine,</hi> is a Waſting from the backe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Navel-galled,</hi> is a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the Nauell, or as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paines</hi> is a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aboue
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or foot-lock.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Poule-evill,</hi> is on the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Necke: and breedeth by ſtripes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pin</hi> or <hi>web,</hi> which couereth the beard of the Eye.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rume,</hi> is taken by cold, &amp; ſo his Teeth will wax looſe, &amp; ſeeme long, &amp; then he cannot eate his meat, but it wil lie in lumps, about his Iaws.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ring-bone,</hi> is a hard griſtle about the Hoofe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quinnaſie,</hi> is ſoreneſſe in the Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Selander,</hi> is a Scab on the Hammes on the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der legges.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shackle-galled,</hi> is on the Paſtorne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spavin,</hi> is on the Ioynt in the hoofes behind.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Splent,</hi> is a ſplend ſinew aboue the fetterlocks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Staggers,</hi> is a dizzineſſe in the head, breeding of cold and of the Yellowes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stranglings,</hi> is a ſwelling in the Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stone,</hi> in a horſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Surbating,</hi> is vnder the Soales of the Feet on the further ſide.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vives,</hi> is a certaine Curnell vnder the eare, or a Canker in the Mouth or Throat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wind-gals,</hi> are Bladders about the fetterlocks.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Yellow,</hi> is a kind of Iaundies, and will cauſe the Eyes to looke yellow, and other parts of the body alſo.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 7. How to judge of the ſickneſſes and impedimets in a horſe, by his doung or ordure.</head>
            <p>I haue found for the moſt part the dung or ordure is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to the food the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth eſpecially for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, for if he run at graſſe, or be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>led in the Stable, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> wil his dung be euermore green, howbeit of a more bright<pb facs="tcp:10523:8"/>and ſometimes again of a more dark colour, and freer from darkneſſe is euer beſt, and doth make appearance of the more ſanity and health of the beaſt, as alſo that is th reby the leſſe ſubiect to conſtiueneſſe, and therfore in better ſtate of body. But if his ordure be very bright and laxatiue, it is an infallible ſigne that he hath eaten ſome thing that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature; as a Feather or ſome naughty worme, ſome Spider or the like unwholeſome thing, otherwiſe he ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of ſome inward co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d which hath formerly lurked in his ſtomacke or body: but if his doung at graſſe or ſoyle be very hard and coſtiue, which he putteth forth with round and hard trattles, then is it a great ſign that he is very hot in his body and inward parts, which may endanger the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or elſe doth ſhew that he hath a ſurfet which he got (before his putting forth) through intemperate riding, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſhing, raw, or euill food, or the like, whereby the horſe is in danger to become morfounded, to haue the yellows, or iaundiſe, or a feauer; which will otherwiſe hardly appeare in him in it's effect vntill his comming into the Stable, at what time due order muſt be taken for ſpéedy preuention. But if your horſe doe féed vpon Straw, then will the colour of his doung be yellow and ſome what hard, long, and well compact, all which be tokens of a healthy and a ſound body; but if it be reddiſh, and excéeding dry, it is a ſigne of enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſickneſſe, by means of a great drought in the body, and ſo alſo if it be thine: but if it be blackiſh, and doth not ſmell ſtrong, then is it a ſign that the horſe is in danger of death. But if your horſe doe féed vpon Hay and Oates, and that he be ſound in body, then will his Excrements be a brown yellow, moyſt, and wel compact but if the browneſſe be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into rediſhneſſe, you may be then well aſſured that he hath ſome diſtemperature in his body, but when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth into blackneſſe, then if preuention be not ſpéedily had, death enſueth: and as touching the ſmell, that falleth out according to the quantity of the prouender you giue him for the more prouender, the ſtronger will be the ſmell of his Ordure, and Peaſe and Beanes will cauſe his Ordure to ſmell ſtronger than Oates, &amp; bread more than any grayn or Pulſe; and the more bread and prouender you giue him, the more perfect and ſound ſhall you kéep him in his body. But if his dung be brown and ſlimy, and ſhine withall, then<pb facs="tcp:10523:9"/>be you aſſured he hath much greace which lyéth in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which Phyſicke muſt fetch away from him, for then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is his bloud putrified, corrupted, or enflamed. But if you doe find by his Excrements that he voydeth vndigeſted ſtuffe, which you may know by the whole corns of Oates, Wheat and other Grayne he ſendeth forth in his doung, then perſwade yourſelfe, that your horſe hath lately taken a formall ſurfet, which may right eaſily bring him to his end, if a diſcréet courſe be not ſpéedily taken: in a word, if his doung be black and hath little or no ſmell, then make you no queſtion but that he is in danger of death, which will ful ſoone after follow, if the greater care be not taken to hinder and preuent the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 8. How to judge of the ſickneſſes or impediments in a horſe by his Stale or Vrine.</head>
            <p>IF he ſhall find his water to be either pale, whitiſh or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not much unlike to the colour of Whey, or fat Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or if it be not very cleare, but ſmelleth ſomwhat ſtrong let the ferrier then be confident the horſe is not ſicke, but ſound and healthy, and in perfect ſtate of body; but if his Vrine be extreame cleare and white, and of the colour of Rock-water, and withall ſlimy, then hath he a taint in his Kidneis, Reines, or back, or elſe he enclineth to the ſtone or elſe he hath ſom ſtoppage in his Kidneys. But if his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be high coloured like to the colour of ſtrong Beer, then is it a token the blood of the horſe is enflamed, and that he is ſubiect to a Feauer, or to ſome ſtrong Surfet: but if it be red and of the colour almoſt of blood, then is the blood more inflamed, which came of ouer hard riding, which may prone very dangerous to his life. But if it be of a pale greeniſh colour thick, and viſcous, then certainely his Backe is growne weake, and he is in danger of a Conſumption of his Steed. But if it be high coloured and nebuled or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſmall Clouds, with a kind of blackneſſe therein, then this doth demonſtrate enſuing ſickneſſe and death, if it be not carefully preuented. But if the Nebuloſity be diſperſed into ſeuerall parts, and not combined as it were into on Maſſe or Body; this then argueth, that the malice of the diſeaſe beginneth to depart, whereby the Ferrier may haue great hope of the health of the Horſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10523:9"/>
            <head>Chap. 9. A diſcription of the number quallity and meaſure of the ſinewes of a horſe.</head>
            <p>IT behooueth vs alſo to deſcribe vnto you the number, quality, and meaſure of the ſinewes of a horſe. From the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>id noſtrils vp to the top of the head, and ſo downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the backe, euen to the crooper comes it great cords or tendons, euery one xii. foote long. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is there two branches and principall ſinewes of the braine, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foure foote. Then from the ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ders to the nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t downwarde two great ſinewes or tendons. And from that ioynt downe to the paſtorns foure great ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>newes. Alſo in the forepart and about his breſt, aſwell within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s without, are x. ſinews, and as many in his hinder parts. Then from the reynes of his backe vnto his ſtones are foure, ſo that in his whole body he hath in all foure and thirty apparant ſinewes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 10. Of the three powers or vertues whereby as well the body of a horſe as every other beaſt is governed.</head>
            <p>THe powers and vertues whereby the body of euery beaſt is gouerned, are in number thrée, that is to ſay, the power Animall, the power Vitall, and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Naturall. The power Animall, is a vertue incident to the braine, which through the ſinewes c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mming like conduite pipes from the braine, diſtributeth féeling and moouing to all the parts of the body. The power Vitall is a vertue belonging to the heart, which giueth life and ſpirite to all the body; and to euery parte thereof, by meanes of the arters, which alſo like conduit pypes doe procéede from the heart, the chiefe fountaine of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:10"/> The power Naturall, is a vertue properly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the liuer, which giueth nutriment vnto all the body, and to euery part thereof, by meanes of the veins, which like wiſe procéed from the liuer like conduit pips, carying the blood from the liuer, which is the fountaine of bloud vnto euery part of the body. Moreouer, the power naturall comprehendeth foure other vertues, that is to ſay, the vertue attractiue, whereby it draweth ſuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inance méet to nouriſh the body, then the vertue reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue whereby it retaineth and kéepeth the ſuſtinance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, thirdly, the vertue digeſtiue, whereby it digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame: and finally the vertue expulſiue, whereby it expelleth excrements, or ſuperfluitys. Thus you ſée that the thrée powers before recyted, be of no ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and therefore the Ferrer had néed to haue a ſpeciall regard vnto them. For if any of them fayle, the beaſt cannot liue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 11. Of the number and ſituation of bones that be in a horſes body.</head>
            <p>EUery Horſe or Oxe, hath in the vpper part of his head two bones, and from his forehead vnto his noſtrills, other two Alſo two nether Iawe bones, and of téeth in all, to the number of xl. that is to ſay, of Iaw téeth, or ſide teeth, xxiiii of tuſhes xiii. of fortéeth, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called the ſhearing téeth xii The ioynt bones, aſwel of the necke as of the backe, be in all twenty two. that is to ſay from the head to the withers, vii. and from thence to the reynes or kidneys. viii. and from thence to the tayle, ſeauen, then is there the great broad hinder bone, called the ſacred bone, which hath xii. ſeames or ioyntures Alſo in the horſes ſhoulder be two great bone called the ſpade bones, and from thence to the forcelles or Canell bones, other two bones and from thence to the firſt ioynt aboue the legges, other two and from thence to the knees two called the thigh bones, and from thence to the paſtornes, other two called the ſhanke bones, and from thence downward to the hooues, be in all xvi. little bones. Then there is a great bone in his breſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10523:10"/>are faſtened xxvi. ribbes. And to the Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>elle behinde be two bones, and from the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayrs to the ioints other two, and alſo two towards the ribbes. From the bending of the hough vnto the legge, are two ſmall bons and from the legge to the two feciles of the legge, other two little bones and from the paſtorns to the hooue ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene little bones. The summe of all the bones, is one hundrad threeſcore and ten.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 12. In what points the art of ſhooing doth conſiſt, and of hooves and of divers kinds thereof.</head>
            <p>THe Art of ſhooing conſiſteth in theſe points, that is to ſay, in paring the hooue well, in making the ſhooe of good ſtuffe, in well faſhoning the webbe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and well piercing the ſame, in fitting the ſhooe vnto the horſes foote, in making nayles of good ſtuffe and faſhoning of the ſame, and finally, in well driuing of the ſaid nayles, and clenching of the ſame. But ſith neither paring nor ſhooing is no abſolute thing of it ſelfe, but hath reſpect vnto the foot, or hooue, (for the ſhooe is to be fitted to the foot, and not the foote to the ſhooe) and that there be diuers kinds of hooues both good and bad, requiring great diuerſity as well of paring as ſhooing.</p>
            <p>Of hooues ſome be perfect and ſome be voperfect The perfect Hooue is that which is round, ſmooth and ſhort, ſo as the Horſe may treade more on the Toe than on the Heele, and alſo right, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hollow within, but not ouer hollow, haue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a narrowe fruſh, and broade Heeles. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Hooue. is that which lacketh any of theſe propertyes beforeſayde, belonging vnto a perfect Hooue. For as touching the firſt point marke. If the Hooue be not round but brode, and ſpreading out of
<pb facs="tcp:10523:11"/>the ſides or quarters, that horſe for the moſt part hath narrow héels, &amp; in continuance of time will be flat footed which is a weake foot, and will not cary a ſhooe long, nor trauell far, but ſoone ſurdate, and by treading more on his heeles, than on his toes, will go low on his paſtorns and ſuch feet through their weakneſſe be much ſubiect to falſe quarters, and to grauelling.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the hooue be not ſmooth, but rugged, and full of circles, like Rammes hornes, then it is not onely vnſeemely to the eye, but alſo it is a ſigne that the foote is in no good temper, but to hot and dry, and thereby per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppes maketh the hooue to be brittle.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if it be long, then it will cauſe the horſe to tread all vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heeles, and to go low on his paſtornes and thereby to breed windgalls.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e hooue be not right, but crooked, that is to ſay, brode without, and narrow within, whereby the horſe is ſplay footed, then it will cauſe the horſe to treade more inward, than outward, and to go ſo cloſe with his ioynts together, as he cannot well trauell without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfering, or perhaps ſtriketh one Leg ſo hard agains another, as he becometh lame. But if he be broad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and narrow without, that is not ſo hurtfull. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it will cauſe him to graueil ſooner on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide than on the inſide,</p>
            <p>Fiftly, if the hooue be flat and not hollow within, then it breedeth ſuch inconueniences, as are before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the firſt vnperfect hooue. And againe if it be ouer hollow, then it will drye the faſter, and cauſe the horſe to be hoouebound. For the ouer hollow hooue is a ſtrait narrow hooue, and groweth vpright, whereby though the Horſe treadeth vpright, and not on his heeles, yet ſuch kind of hoous will dry ouer faſt, vnleſſe they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſtopt, and cauſe the horſe to be hooubound, which lameth them, making them to halt.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, if the truth be broad, then the heeles bee weake, and ſo ſoft as you may almoſt bend them together and then the horſe will neuer tread boldly on the ſtones or hard ground.</p>
            <p>Seauenthly, &amp; laſtly, if the heels be narrow, the be ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der &amp; the horſe will grow to be hooubound.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10523:11"/>
            <head>Chap. 13. Of paring and ſhooing the perfect hooue and forefeet, and how to make the ſhooes and nayles.</head>
            <p>FIrſt pare the feat of the ſhooe, ſo euen and plaine as may be, to the intent that the ſhooe may ſit cloſe and not beare in one place more than in an other and take more of the toe, than of the heele, to the intent that the heeles be higher then the toe, becauſe all the waight of the horſes, fore-body lyeth vpon the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and heeles of the forefeete. And therefore thoſe parts ſhould be moſt mayntained, and taken off with the butter as little as may be. For the paring of the héels, being naturally thinner, and more tender than the toe, doth greatly weaken them: but the toe being naturally thicke and hard, would be pared ſo thinne almoſt as the edge of a knyfe. But in paring of the hinder féet, a clean contrary order is to be obſerued.</p>
            <p>Then make your ſhooe of ſpruſe or ſpaniſh Yron, with a brode webbe, fitting it to the foote, and let the ſpongs be thicker, and more ſubſtanciall then any other part; of the ſhooe, yea, and alſo ſomewhat broade, ſo as the quarters on hoth ſides may diſbord, that is to ſay, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare without the hooue a ſtrawes bredth, to gard the coffin, which is the ſtrength of the hooue, and onely beareth the ſhooe, and when you come to the piercing thereof, ſpeare not to pierce it from the quarter to the hard toe, but not backwards toward the heele and pierce it ſo as the holes may be wider on the outſide than on the inſide, and that the cyrcle of the piercing may be more diſtant from the edge of the toe, then from the edge of the quarter, whereas it beginneth, becauſe the hooue is thicker foreward then backward, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more hold to be taken. And as touching the nayls then make them alſo of the ſame Iron beforeſaid, the heads wherof would be ſquare and not fully ſo brode beneath as is aboue, but anſwerable to the piercing<pb facs="tcp:10523:12"/>holes, as the head of the nayles may enter in and fill the ſame, appearing aboue the ſhooe no more than the bredth of the backe of a knife, ſo ſhall they ſtand faſt without ſhogging, and endure longer, and to that end the ſtamp that firſt maketh the holes, and the perſchill that pierc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and alſo the necks of the nayls, would be of one ſquare faſhion and bignes, that is to ſay, great aboue and ſmall beneath, which our common Smithes doe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard, for when they pirce a ſhooe, they make the holes as wide on the inſide, as on the outſide, and their nayls with ſo great a ſhouldering by drying them ouer hard vpon the nayle toole, as the heads or rather necks of the ſayd nayles, can not enter into the holes, for to ſay the truth, a good nayle would haue no ſhouldering at all, but be made with a playne and ſquare necke, ſo as it may iuſtly fit and fill the piercing hole of the ſhooe. For otherwiſe the head of the nayle ſtanding high, and the necke thereof being weake, eyther it breaketh off or elſe bendeth vpon euery light occaſion, ſo as the ſhooe thereby ſtandeth looſe from the hooue and is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt. Moreouer, the thankes of the nayles would be ſomewhat flatte, and the pointes ſharp without hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowneſſe or flaw, and ſtiffer towards the head aboue, than beneath. And when you driue, driue at the firſt with ſtrokes and with a light hammer, vntill the naile be ſomewhat entred, and in ſhooing fine delicat horſes it ſhall not bee amiſſe to greaſe the pointes of the nayle with a little ſoft greaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the nayles may enter the more eaſily, and driue the two Talon nayles firſt. Then looke whether the ſhooe ſtandeth right or not, which you ſhall perceiue in beholding the Fruſh, for if the ſpongs on both ſides, be equally diſtant from the Fruſh, then it ſtandeth right, if not then amend it and ſet the ſhooe right, and ſtanding right, driue in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nayle, that done, let the horſe ſet downe his foote againe, and looke round about it to ſée whether it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the horſes foot in all places, and whether the horſe teradeth euen and iuſt on it or not. And if you ſée that the ſhooe doth not furniſh euery part equally, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10523:12"/>appeareth more of one ſide than of another. Then make the Horſes other foote to be lifted vp, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he may ſtand the more ſtedily vppon that foote, and ſo ſtanding, ſtrike him on the hooue with your hammer on that ſide that the ſhooe is ſcant, and that ſhall make the ſhooe to come that way. The ſhooe then ſtanding ſtraight and iuſt, driue in the reſt of all the nayles to the number of eight, that is to ſay, foure on the on ſide, and foure on another, ſo as the points of the nayles may ſéeme to ſtand in the out ſide the hooue euen and iuſt one by another; as it were in a Cyrenler line, and not out of order, like the teeth of a ſaw whereof one is bent one way and clinch them ſo as the clinches may be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the hooue, which by cutting the Hooue with the point of a knyfe, a little beneath the appearing of the nayle you may eaſely doe. That done with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ape, pare the hooue round, ſo as the edge of the ſhooe may be ſéene round about.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 14. Of paring and ſhooing the hinder feet.</head>
            <p>FOr the paring of the hinder féete, is cleane contrary, to the forféete, for the weakeſt part of the hinder foote is the toe, and therefore in paring the hinder foote, the toe muſt be alwayes more ſpared than the héeles.</p>
            <p>Then make the ſhooe fitte for the hooue in ſuch forte as is before ſaid, ſauing that it would be always ſtrongeſt towards the toe, and it muſt be pierced nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the héele than the toe, becauſe as I haue ſaid before, that the toe is alwayes the weakeſt part of the hinder foot. Alſo let the out ſide of the hinder ſhooe be made with a Calkin, not ouer high, but let the other ſponge be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable vnto the Calkin, that is to ſay, as high in a manner as the Calkin, which Calkin is to keepe the horſe from flyding, But then it may not be ſharpe poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but rather flatte and handſomely turned vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:13"/>
            <head>Chap. 15. How to keepe the hoove of a horſe moiſt in the ſtable, and the receit of the oyntment.</head>
            <p>AS Horſes hoous do many times take harme through the necligence or vnskilfulneſſe of the Ferrer, in euill paring or ſhooing the ſame, euen ſo they take no leſſe harme many times through the necligence of the kéeper for lack of ſtopping, and kéeping the foreféete moyſt, for the hinder féete moſt commonly are kept to moyſt, by meanes that the doung and ſtale is ſuffered to lye continually at their héeles. But the forféete ſtand continually dry, whereby the horſe becommeth brittle hooued, yea, and many times hoouebound, which a good keeper will not ſuffer, but be mindfull to ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, either with horſe doung, or Cow doung, yea, and alſo to waſh them cleane without, with water, and then to anoynt them with ſome good ſupplying oyntment, as this here following preſcribeth.</p>
            <p>Take of Turpentine, of ſheeps ſewet, of each halfe a pound, of vnwroght wax halfe a quarterne, and of Sallet oyle halfe a pint. Boyle all theſe together in a potte, ſturring them continually vntill they be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mingled together. Then take it from the fyre, and let it coole, and being cold, preſerue it in the ſame pot, or elſe in ſome other, to the intent that you may haue it ready euery ſecond day to annoynt all the coffins of the Horſes Hooues round about, but firſt waſh their hooues faire and cleane and ſuffer no durt to remaine vpon them, then being dryed with a cloth annoynte them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10523:13"/>
            <head>The ſiixt Chapter. Approved remedies for the curing of all kindes of diſeaſes, hurts, maimes, or malidies, or griefes in Horſes.</head>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Galling of a Horſe-backe.</head>
               <p>TAke Butter, vineger and Bay-ſalt, and melt them together, and lay on the horſe backe warme: then ſtrow vpon it sut, or the poulder of a clay wall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>ob.</hi> of turmericke, bruiſe it, a handfull of Bay-ſalt, and a handfull of Sut, with two handfuls of Oatemeale, mingle it with Vrine, and make it into a Cake as well as you can, and then vpon a hot harth bake it till it be burnt blacke, then beate it in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to poulder; and when you haue waſhed your horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe with Lee very hot or Chamber Lee, then ſtrow on the poulder: and when the poulder is almaſt gone, dreſſe it as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>If it bee feſtred, take Yeeſt, Honey, the white of an Egge,, and ſut; mingle them together, and make a plaiſter thereof, and lay it to the dead fleſh: then ſtraw on Verdigreace, and renew it once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a pottle of Vergis, two penny worth of gréene Copris, and boile it to a pint and a halfe: waſh<pb facs="tcp:10523:14"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a man on horseback</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10523:14"/>and ſearch the hole therewith, and fill the hole<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with Red Lead,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo let it remaine thrée dayes vntouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then waſh it with the ſame, and fill it againe with Red Lead: and ſo euery other day waſh it with that Water, not made ſo ſtrong of the Copris; and lay thereon Red Lead, this will heale it though it be gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To heale any canker or ſore in a horſe.</head>
               <p>Take of the ſtrongeſt Beere a pint, put it into a quarter of a pound of Allum: and halfe a hand full of Sage: Seethe it to the one halfe, then take out the Sage leaues: this will heale any Canker or Sore in a horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To heale any cut in a Horſe.</head>
               <p>Take a quarter of a pound of freſh Butter, of tarre and blacke Sope, halfe ſo much of each, and a little turpentine: boyle them altogether (but the Sope) and as ſoone as you take it from the fire, put in the Sope and then uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a horſe wrung in the wales.</head>
               <p>Take Butter and ſalt, and boile them together till they are blacke, then powre it on hot: then take vp a flake of Horſe doung that is hot, and loy it on the ſore backe, and ſo dreſſe him till he be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For fretting on the belly which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with galling of the foregirt.</head>
               <p>This commeth with the fore Girt, and it ſtoppeth the blood which is in the principall veines, called the plate Veines, which doe runne length wayes, take Oyle of Bayes, and Oyle of Balme, two<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10523:15"/>ounces of Pitch, two ounces of tarre, one ounce of Roſen: mingle them altogether, and annoynt the fore bowels, then take Flaxe and lay vpon it, and ſeare it with a hot Iron, but take héed it be not too hot, for feare of burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Thiſtulaes.</head>
               <p>When you firſt perceiue it to ſwell, then ſcald it with Honey and ſhéepes ſuet, but ſcald it very much, this will keepe it from bréeding.</p>
               <p>Then take and ſlit it in the ueather end of the ſore and put as much <hi>Mercury Sublimatum</hi> as a Peaſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it with Sallet Oyle, laying it on with a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; after that take verdigreace foure penny worth, Vitriall ob. Lead thrée penny worth, beate theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and euery day waſh the wound with Copris water made with Copris and Elder leaues in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and with the inner gréene barke in Winter: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter waſhing, take the powder, and put it on the ſore, and after it droppe on a little Oyle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the outtermoſt gréene ſhels of Walnuts, and put them in a tubbe, ſtrowing thrée or foure handfull of Bay-ſalt upon them, ſome on the bottome, ſome on the middle, and ſome on the top, and ſo kéepe them all the yeare: and when you will vſe them, take a pint of them, and a little bay ſalt, and halfe a quarter of a pound of blacke Sope, with halfe a ſpoonefull of May butter (and for want thereof, other butter and incorporate them together, and then ſpread it on the ſore: but two houres before you lay it on, annoynt the Sore with a little Venice-turpentine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A medicine to kill the thiſtula cleane, cankers, or fouleſores</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:10523:15"/>Take vnguentum <hi>Egyptiacum</hi> which is made of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, a pint, Vineger halfe a pint Allum a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound, and verdigreace an ounce and halfe, ſee the them altogether, till they be thicke and a tawny colour; this is called <hi>Egyptiacum:</hi> And to made it the ſtrongeſt way, is to put Subl. an ounce make in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Arſnicke two ſcruples, and boyle it together.</p>
               <p>This ſtrongeſt is for thiſtulaes, Cankers, and foule Soares: and the firſt may be uſed in the Mouth, but not that which is made of
<hi>Sublimatum</hi> and Arſenicke; for they are poyſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Tent to put into the hollow place of</head>
               <p>Take of Sublimatum well powdered, one ounce, the middeſt of well leauened Bread ſtake baked iiii. or of Neuin fenne drammes; mingle them together with a little Roſe-water, and make Tents thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and drie them vpon a tile, and then take it to uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To make a Lee for the ſame, or water to kill a Thiſtula at the bottome.</head>
               <p>Take Lée, honey Roch Allum, and Mercury, and ſéethe them together: and apply it to the thiſtula at the bottome thereof,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Alſo to drie a thiſtula, take Rew, Wine, Goats doung, and Beane flowre, and ſeeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> together, and lay it on, and this will dre it vp.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To ſinck-a Thiſtula.</head>
               <p>Take firſt and ſeare it with this marke <hi>O</hi> or ſuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10523:16"/>like, and then take Roſen, Sheepes fallow, and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and boyle them together, and lay it on very hot with a Cloth: this will ſinke it downe againe. This is good alſo for a Windgall: take and picke it out (but beweare of Sinnewes) and then lay it on; but not ſo hot, but very reaſonable: and this will kéepe it cleaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Thiſtula in the head.</head>
               <p>Take the iuyce of houſe-léeke and dippe a locke of Wooll in it, and put the locke of Wooll in his Eare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and bind it faſt, vſe this once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>If there bea any inflammation in the Eares, or that it groweth to an inpoſtumation in that place, you ſhall boyle the rootes of Mallowes in water till they waxe tender, then bruiſe them, and ſtraine out the water cleane and being warme giue it the Horſe to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To know the Bottes.</head>
               <p>When you thinke that your Horſe hath the Boſs, looke in his mouth: and ſmell on his breath, for it will ſtinke, and his mouth will be full of ſlime.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To cure the Bottes.</head>
               <p>Take as much blacke Sope as a Walnut, as much Brimſtone beaten, and a little Garlike, and put it in good Ale, and giue it to the Horſe blood warme: but for a Mare with foale, then take brimſtone, ſut, and Garlike, with out ſope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:10523:16"/>Take a handfull of new Hens doung<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a quart of good ſtale drinke, and all to bray it with your hands: than take a good handfull of bay Salt, and put two Egges to it, and bray them together, and giue it your horſe to drinke in a horne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of milke, of Saffron, <hi>ob</hi> of Allum ob. beate them together, and giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To kill the wormes in the maw.</head>
               <p>Take the crops of young broome, and of Sauin and Grunſell, of each a quantity: then crop them ſmall, and giue it him with his provender euening &amp; morning let him and not drinke for a good ſpace after.</p>
               <p>If he have the long wormes, take milke, brimſtone and honey, and giue him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the wormes in the Coddes.</head>
               <p>Take the guts of a young Pullet; and caſt it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his mouth faſting, and make him to ſwallow them downe: doe this thrée mornings together, but let him not drinke nor eate in fiue houres after.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to giue him freſh broome in his prouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſalt water to drinke.</p>
               <p>Others doe giue him of gréene Willow, or greene Réed ſo eate, and in diſgeſtion of the meate, he ſhall caſt out the Wormes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Garbidge of a young henne or Pigeon while it is warme, rowle it firſt in a little Sope, and and after in Bay-ſalt, and force it downe his threate: and it will helpe him. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:10523:17"/>
               <head>To know when a Horſe hath the wormes.</head>
               <p>Take vp his vpper lippe, and you ſhall ſee many ſmall blew veines, greater and bigger than the worme veines by a great deale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that hath the Trunchions.</head>
               <p>Let him drinke Heunes doung, Mint, Sage, and Rue: and let him blood in the Noſtriles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe giue him Sauin or Sothernewood to drinke; and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take ob. of Arment, ob. of Honey, ob. of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niricke, ob. good ſtale Ale: mingle them together, and tie vp the horſe head on high, and giue it him to drinke with a horne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Bliſters.</head>
               <p>Take the ſuyce or ground Iuie, with ſo much Brimſtone, a quantity of tarre, and ſo much Allum: put it altogether, and lay it to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Bards.</head>
               <p>If they grow long, they will hinder his féeding: they doe vſe to clippe them with a paire of ſheares, and then wath his Mouth with water and Salt: and that will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Staggers.</head>
               <p>You ſhall perceiue them by beating his head, and he will be as though he were hlind.</p>
               <p>Take garlike, rue, and bay-ſalt, and beat them groſly put vineger into it, &amp; put it into the horſes eares, &amp; then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10523:17"/>wet wooll in his mediciue, and ſtop his eares therewith and bind them cloſe, and let it bee ſo 24. houres, and then pull out his tongue and waſh it with vineger, to make him haue a good ſtomake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Firſt take a wiſpe of wet hay, and burne it vnder his noſe that the ſmoake may fume into his head, then take halfe a handfull of Salandine, and as much hearb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ace, thrée or foure cloues of Garlike, and a little
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Salt, and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>p them together, and put thereto
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> or fiue ſpoonefull of vineger or vergis: then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it into the horſes Eares: and tye the Eares cloſe that no ayre may come in: let it continue in his Eares a day and a night, and then let him blood.</p>
               <p>Or elſe take Rue and Salandine, of each alike, and white Salt, and ſtampe them together, and put into his eares, and binde them vp for two houres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take oyle of bitter Almonds, i. oz. <hi>di.</hi> of Oxe gall, ii. Drammes of blacke <hi>Ellebor</hi> ſtamped, <hi>ob</hi> of graines of Caſterum, of Vineger, and of veriuyce five drammes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſéeth them altogether till the vineger be conſumed, then ſtraine them, and put it into his Eares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the paine in the head, or ſtifeling.</head>
               <p>Keepe his head warme and let him drinke warme water mingled with wheat-meale, or Fennel-ſeede, and blow it into his Noſe with a quill, and ſome powder of Ellabar, Snéeſing powder, mixed together with ſome pepper: then take a pint of malmeſie, the whites and yolkes of fiue new layd Egges, one head of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like bruiſed, ſmall pepper, Cinamon and Nutmegs beaten fine, and a quantity of ſweet butter: mingle them together, and giue it him to drinke three dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10523:18"/>but let him not drinke in foure houres after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the wanders.</head>
               <p>Take halfe a buſhell of Barly, and ſet on the fire in a panne, and put t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>reto running water, and euer as the water waſteth, put in more, ſo that the Barly be couered with water, and let it ſeeth till the Barley be broken: then take a little Poke or Sacke, and put the Barley therein, and lay the ſame on the Horſe ridge on length from the Maine to the Cropper, all hot: and let it lye till it be cold, and there let it lye a nigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and a day, and put the Horſe into a greene Yard ſome <hi>xxiiii.</hi> houres, and there he will wallow: and then take him in, and he will be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Yellowes.</head>
               <p>You ſhall know them by the white of his Eye, which will be yellow, or elſe by his tongue, which will haue yellow veines, or put vp his vpper Lippe, and you ſhall ſée veines yellow.</p>
               <p>Take two races of Turmericke, and ob. of Saffron and put to it a pint of ſtrong Beere or Ale, and warme it blood-warme, and giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Turmericke a cloue and <hi>di</hi> and <hi>di.</hi> a dozen thaines of Saffron, one or two Cloues, and ſixe ſpoone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of vineger or vergis: and put each in Eare three ſpoonfuls, and ſtop his eares with blacke wooll: and then tye them faſt ſeven or eight dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take long Pepper, graines, turmericke, and Licoris beaten in powder: put them into ſtrong Beere and giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:10523:18"/>
               <head>For the paines or Crotches, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by heat, and ſudden cold upon it,</head>
               <p>The paines appeare aboue the Hoofe: you ſhall know them by the Haire ſtanding right vp, you muſt take vp the ſhackle veine on both ſides, then take the ſoft Row of a red Herring, and Muſtard, and blacke Sope, and boile theſe in vineger and make a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſter, and lay it to the ſore.</p>
               <p>There is no Veine betweene the Poſterne and the Hoofe but the Shanke Veine, and the Veine which ſerueth for the Crotches muſt bee taken vp on the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and the outſide.</p>
               <p>Waſh it firſt with warme Vrine, then drie it with a Cloth, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ippe away a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the hayres o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by place; then rubbe and chafe it all ouer, and make faſt his feete, and rubbe the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace grieued with But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and tarre boyling together vpon a Clout tied on a ſtickes end and ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e it well therewith: vſe this once or twice a day, till it be whole.</p>
               <p>Butter and honney molten together, is good to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynt an Horſe for paines, or Crotches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther for the ſame.</head>
               <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke a pound of Hogges greace, i. d. worth of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digreace ii. oz of muſtard. di a pound of oyle de bay, a quarter of a pound of Naruell, di. a pound of Honey di. a pound of Engliſh Waxe, i. oz. of Arſenicke, ii. oz of Red Lead, halfe a pint of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: boyle all theſe together, and make an Oyntment of it: C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ippe the Horſes legge bare, and lay this medicin to it very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Courded legges, or ſcratches.</head>
               <p>Take vp the ſheines beneath the knee, and let<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10523:19"/>him blood as much as you thinke good, then knit the Veine aboue and beneath, and annoynt the legges with this oyle following.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for theſame.</head>
               <p>Take Frankinſence, and Roſen, and freſh greace, and boyle them together, and ſtraine it: and keepe it to your vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Drinke to raiſe a Horſe, or for a Horſe that is ſicke.</head>
               <p>Take two penny-worth of Pepper, two penny worth of Saffron, two penny-worth of Annis-ſeedes two penny worth of turmericke, a penny-worth of long Pepper, two penny-worth of treacle, a penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth of Licoris, a good quantity of penny reyall and Archangell: Giue him theſe with the yolkes of Egges in milke to drinke, And for Neate Cattell, giue theſe to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Scurfet Horſe.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of Beere or Ale, two penny-worth of Sallet oyle, and as much Dragon water, a penny-worth of treacie: make them warme vpon the coales and put into it a penny-worth of Horſe Spices: and giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Hide-bound Horſe.</head>
               <p>This commeth by ouermuch working, ill dyer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and naughty dreſſing take Fen-creeke, turme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, Annis ſeedes, Bayes, Licoris, and Cummin beate all theſe together, and giue him one ſpoonefull of all theſe in Ale or Beere blood warme. this is alſo good for the cough: this will alſo keepe him from it, If you uſe to giue if him before the diſeaſe commeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:10523:19"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take away ſome blood with the Flem; then giue him ſome warme meaſhes morning and euening, and giue him Malt ſodden in water together, or branne and water, or ſome wheat ſodden with Barly in water and it will helpe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the hoofe-bound.</head>
               <p>You ſhall raiſe the hoofe aboue from the toppe to the ſoale in foure or fiue places, that the Water may come out: Some doe raiſe it round with a ſharpe knife, and along downeward, and then rubbe it well with Salt once or twice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a looſe Hoofe.</head>
               <p>Take Tarre thrée ſpoonefull of Roſen, a quarter of a pound of Tanſie, Rue, of red Mints, of Sothern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, of each halfe a handfull: beate all them together namorter, and put there to halfe a pound of butter, i, d. worth of Virgins wax: then fry them altogether, and binde it to the Hoofe for eight dayes, and it will eure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a brittle hoofe.</head>
               <p>If your Horſe haue a brittle Hoofe, it is becauſe it is too hot or too dry; and doth ſtand a day in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unſtopped.</p>
               <p>Take Oxe-doung and temper it with Vineger, and binde it warme all ouer vnto the Féete, and vnder the ſoales of the Féete, on the next day uſe him ſo againe; ſo uſe it for a wéeke together, and it will helpe him: vſe to ſtoppe his Féete with Oxe or Cow doung, or his owne; and let him ſtand ſo a moneth.</p>
               <p>Or, take the fat of Bacon, and temper it with<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10523:20"/>Turpentine, and annoynt his Féete therewith; which is very good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A Medicine for the Cough, or morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the chine.</head>
               <p>Kéepe your Horſemeatleſſe ouer night, then take a a pint and a halfe of milke, thrée he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ads of Garlike p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lled and ſtamped, boyle them to the halfe: giue it to your Horſe, and ſome at his noſe, then runne a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a mile, then reſt him; and after that, runne him thrée times more, euery time reſting him: then put him into a ſtable, and keepe him very warme, giue him no water till ofternoone, then giue him good Meſh and ſo vſe him with Meſhes three dayes, and giue him no water but alwayes warme, for three dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Hornehound. Licoris, and Annis ſeeds, in powder make Balles thereof with freſh Butter and giue it your Horſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take wheat flowre, Annis ſeeds, and Licoris, being ſtamped in a morter. Fiue or ſixe cloues of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like being bruiſed: mixe all theſe together, and make a Praiſter of them, and rowle them in balles as big as a Walnut: then pull out his tongue, and caſt the balles downe his throate three or foure of them at a time: and giue him two new layd Egges after them ſhels and all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Glaunders.</head>
               <p>Take ſwines greace cleane clarified, and as much oyle of bay as a Walnut: giue it him to drinke with faire water, luke warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:10523:20"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take of Ellecampana, Annis ſeeds, and Licoris of each i.d. worth, boyle them in three pints of ſtrong Ale or Beere, vnto two pints or leſſe: then put into it a quarter of a pint of Sallet oyle, and giue it him to drinke blood warme</p>
               <p>Then take Enfordium in a Quill, and blow it up into his noſe, and within three dayes after, take muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard, Vineger, and Butter, and boyle them together: put thereto halfe an ounce of Pepper, and giue it him to drinke. Uſe the one Medicine one weeke, and the other another; and ride to worke him eaſile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another fer the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a quantite of Annis ſeeds, Kicoris, and Elle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campana roots;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong pepper and Garlike, of each a like, with three Egges, and ſome butter, a quantity of malmeſie, and ſome ſtrong Ale mixt together; and make it warme, and ſo giue it him, and keepe him warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Seeth a handfull of pilled Earlike in Milke, and put a peece of Butter thereto, and ſome Ale: and ſtirre them all together, and giue it him faſting, and ride him ſoftly a while after, and then ſet him vp: but keepe him warme nine dayes after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the ſtrangies.</head>
               <p>Cut him betwéene the Iawes, and take out the Kernels and waſh the place every day with béere and butter, and ſtoppe it vp as long as you can, and giue him new milke and Garlike to drinke, and the iuyce of the leaues of Birch withall; or in winter, the barke of Birch: alſo ſmother him with the fume of Maſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icke<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10523:21"/>or Frankinſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Farſey.</head>
               <p>Take blacke Sope, Arſenicke, vnſtaked Lime, verdigreace, and Red Lead: worke theſe together, and lay them to the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take thrée ounce of Quickſiluer, and put it into a bladder, with two ſpoonefulls of the iuyce of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range or Lemmons, and ſhake them together to coole the Quickſiluer: then take halfe a pound of freſh Hogges grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and of Vergis and ounce: put all theſe in a Tréede diſh, and worke them well together: then anoynt the Knots with this Oyntment till they rot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then let them out with a ſharpe Knife, and anoynt them ſtill: and put into his eare the iuyce of Rag-wéed, and they will dry vp. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A drinke for the Farſey:</head>
               <p>Let him blood in the necke of both ſides, foure fingers from the head, and giue him this drinke.</p>
               <p>Take a Gallon of faire water, and put therein a good handfull of Rue, and a ſpoone full of Hempſéeds and bruiſe them into a morter altogether, and ſeeth it till the halfe be conſumed: and when it is cold, giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Farſey.</head>
               <p>Take blacke Sope, Muſtard made of ſharpe Wine or Vineger, and Red Lead, mixe all theſe together, and anoynt the veines all along, rubbe it euer with an hot Iron made of purpoſe, but very thicke: rubbe the Medicine much in with the Iron, being red hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:10523:21"/>
               <head>To deſtroy the Farſey,</head>
               <p>Take the iuyce of hemlocke a good quantity, and bray them together, and put into the eares, &amp; pricke the knots and put in ſalt, and giue him drinke with ſwéet Wort, Fennell and Treacle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe foote, that is wronged in the foote locke.</head>
               <p>Séeth a quart of brine till the foame riſe, then ſtraine it and put thereto an handful of Tanſie, as much of mall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ows a ſaucerful of hony, &amp; a quarter of a pound of ſhéeps Tallow: ſtir all theſe on the fire til the Hearbs are well ſodden, and all hot, lay it to the Ioynt, &amp; then lay a cloth ouer it, and it will be whole in three dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a wrench in the foot-locke.</head>
               <p>Take Pompilion, naruile, &amp; black ſope, of each alike. &amp; heate them hot on the fire and then a noynt him therwith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a horſe that is Stiffed or hipped,</head>
               <p>Take a pound of <hi>Bolearmoniacke,</hi> on quarter of red wine vineger, ſix egs beaten ſhels and all, two penny-worth of Engliſh honey, as much <hi>Venice</hi> Turpentine, one quart of flowre, one good handfull of bay-ſalt, and put all theſe in a pot, and kéepe it cloſe all night, and the next day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play ſome of it to the hurt, dreſſing it once a day for nine dayes together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a horſe that is foundred.</head>
               <p>Take verdigreace, Turpentine, and ſallet-oyle, two or thrée ſpoonefuls of Hogs greace, and bées wax one oz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boile a together, and ſo dip flax or towin it, and ſtuffe his féete there with, and let him blood in the toes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:10523:22"/>Plucke off his ſhooes, and pare hollow his Féet nigh to the quicke, then race him with a crooked Launce from the héele to the toe in two or thrée places on both ſides of the Hoofe, and let him bléed well: then clap two or thrée hard Egges to it as hard as hee may ſuffer it: and as they coole, lay on more: and then lay hot horſe dung vpon them and about his féete, and hee will ſoone recover if you giue him reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a horſe that is foundred in his feet.</head>
               <p>Take tarre, neats-foot oyle, and the yolkes of egs, i.d. worth of verdigreace, and ſome Wheat bran, and boils theſe together, and bind them vnder his foote very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>If he foundred in his body.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>ob</hi> of Garlike ii, d. worth of pouder of Pepper-ii. d. worth of powder ginger .ii. d. worth of graines brut, ſed, and put into a bottle of ſtale ale the beſt you can get and giue it him to drinke, and litter him to the belly and lay-clothes on him as many as he can beare: and let him blood on the ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For blindneſſe</head>
               <p>Take two dry tile ſtones, and rubbe them together and blow the powder of it with a quill into his eyes thrée or foure times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the webbe in the eye.</head>
               <p>Take the lean of a gammon of bacon, and dry it, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of make powder, and vſe the powder, and it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the pearle in the eye,</head>
               <p>Take the iuice of ground-iuy, the iuice of ſalandine, and womans Milke, and put it into the eyes, and it wil alſo cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Maw in the eyes.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:10523:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>Make a plaiſter of the iuyce of ground-iuie, and of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie-berries ſtamped in a Morter, beaten with wine or water: and plaiſterwiſe lay it one the eye or eyes even<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing and morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Some take a Néedle and a double thréed, and thruſt the needle through the filme of the eye wherein the Cruſh groweth; which pull out, laying it on your fingers end, and holding the Needle and thréed ſtraight, and ſo cut away the hard matter a penny bredth, but beware you cut not away the hard fat, which is the waſh of the eye: neither cut the Filme wherein the Eye groweth; but cut betweene the filme and the cruſh, and then ſquirt in beere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Canker in the Eye.</head>
               <p>Take roch Allum &amp; gréene copris, of each alike boyle them in thrée pints of running water, vntill the one halfe be conſumed; then take it from the fire, and once a day waſh his eyes therewith, being made luke-warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a ſtroake in the eye.</head>
               <p>Lay thereto the iuyce of Smallage, Fennell, and the white of an Egge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a windgall.</head>
               <p>Take and cut the Skinne, then take a ſpoonefull of Oyle de. bay, one ſpoonefull of turpentine, i. d. worth of Verdigreace the white of an Egge, and a quarter of an ounce of Red Leade: boyle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it will make a Salue, lay the ſame to the place where you did cut him.
<hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Firſt clppe off the Haire bare, then cut it the length of a B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane, and let it out: but beware of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:10523:23"/>Sinnewes that you cut not them: then haue ready molten Roſen, Sheepes tallow, and brimſtone, boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together: then lay on this medicine, but beware it bee not too hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Spauin.</head>
               <p>Take Muſtardſeede, and Oyle de Bay, and Cow doung, the rootes of Mallowes, a quantity of Turpentine, <hi>di.</hi> oz. of
<hi>Bolearmoniacke,</hi> beate them to powder, and worke them together, and binde them hot to the Spauin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the blood Spauin, and bone Spauin.</head>
               <p>Take vp the veine aboue and beneath the ioynt, and let it bléed well, then knit vp the veines, and annoynt them with butter till they bee whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the bone Spauin.</head>
               <p>For the Bone Spauine, pricke it with a ſharpe pointed Knife, then take a peece of candle, and lay a peece of browne Paper vpon it, and with a hot Iron melt the tallow, and after annoynt it with butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For inflammation of the Coddes.</head>
               <p>Boyle Groundſell in wine and vineger, and ſo bath him therewith, and vſe to ride him into the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of good alewort, and ſet it on the fire, with the crums of brown bread ſtrongly leauened, and a handfull of Commin (or more) in powder: make a plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all theſe and beane flower, and apply it to the griefe as hot as it may be ſuffered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:10523:23"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take new cow doung and ſéeth it in milke; then make a Playſter, and lay it vpon the greife as hot vpon the ſwelling as may bee:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For ſwelling in the Coddes.</head>
               <p>Let him aſſaile a mare, and give him no prouender, and let him blood aboue the great veine betweene the Hippes, and lay thereto hard egges in his owne doung and make a plaiſter of the ſame, and lay it to the Cods, and if it helpe him not, let him ſtand in the water halfe an houer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Strangullion.</head>
               <p>Take bread and bayes, of Laurel, and temper them together with may butter, and giue him there of three dayes together, and he ſhall bee whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For feſtring of the ſore.</head>
               <p>Take lime and tough horſe doung, and temper them together with Pepper and the white of an egge, and lay it to the ſore fiue dayes, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A drinke for the ſtone.</head>
               <p>Take a pint of white wine, halfe a pint of bur feede and beate them ſmall, ii oz. of Parſely ſeede, halfe a handfull of hyſope, halfe an oz. of blacke ſope: mingle theſe together, and warme it, and giue it him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the ſtone Collicke, and fret.</head>
               <p>Take vnſet leekes, and ſtampe them ſmall, and Sope, milke, and butter, and give it the horſe: it will make him piſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:10523:24"/>
               <head>For a horſe that cannot ſtale.</head>
               <p>Take a Nutmeg, and a handfull of parſely, ſéed, beate them in powder, and a handfull of butter, and heate it in good Ale, and giue it him blood-warme, and hee ſhall ſtale at eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the ſtone and to make him piſſe.</head>
               <p>Take the ſeede of Smallage, Parſely <hi>Saxefrace,</hi> the rootes of <hi>philudendula,</hi> Cherryſtone Kernels, Grun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellſeedes, and broome ſeede, of euery one alike much: make them in fine powder, and giue it him in white Wine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that cannot dung.</head>
               <p>Take eleuen leaues of Lorell, and ſtampe them in a Morter, and giue it him to Drinke in ſtrong ſtale Ale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Barly and ſeethe it in the iuyce of Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folly, and giue him the Barly to eate and the iuyce to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Or elſe, take and let him blood, and boyle the blood with the powder of the pill of Pomgranats, and put in ſome Wheate: hen ſtraine it, and giue it him to drinke three or foure mornings, but let him not trauaile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the powder of Licoris and Annis ſeedes,<pb facs="tcp:10523:24"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the farrier's profession</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of a farrier's tools</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10523:25"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of a man on horseback</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:10523:25"/>rouled vp in Honey and giue him thrée or foure bals of them at a time, pulling out his Tongue, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it in his throat: It looſeth his breath and ſetteth his winde at libertie, and purgeth the cold and ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and expelleth the Glaunders. Bruſed Licoris, Annis ſeedes, Garlike bruiſed, a little Sallet oyle, and Honey giuen blood warme in Milke cureth many diſeaſes and kéepeth him from more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a Horſe that is broken winded.</head>
               <p>Take a Hedgehogge and ſplit him and take out his guttes, and dry them vp in an Oven untill you make powder of them, giue it to your Horſe to drinke in a pint of ſtrong Ale, a part thereof: then take Bals of Annis ſeeds and Licoris rowled in butter, and caſt them downe-his throat, and waſh his Oates in good Ale or Beere, then take Commin, Annis ſeedes, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coris and Sentalie, and make powder of them, and ſtrew thrée ſpoonefull in his Oates, being moiſt: uſe this ſame Fourtéene dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another if he be purſey.</head>
               <p>Take Molline or Long wort; and make a powder thereof, and giue it him to drinke with water, and it wil heale him.</p>
               <p>Or you may take the Powder of <hi>Genſian</hi> at the Apthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, and that wil heale him alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a horſe pricked with a Naile.</head>
               <p>Take out the hoofe til you come to the bottome, or Veine; then take Turpentine. i. oz. Tarre i. oz. Pitch i. oz. Beefe Sewet i. oz. and one head of Garlike<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: Boyle them altogether, and lay them to it ſo hot as may bee ſuffered: and if it chance to breake out aboue the Hoofe, then take the ſaid medicine, and annoynt it therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:10523:26"/>
               <head>To heale a Mangie Horſe.</head>
               <p>Let him blood on both ſides his Necke, then cutte the Skinne in the middeſt of the Fore-head two fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers broad, then raiſe the Skinne on both ſides, and put in ſlices of Angelica roote, or Elecampana; leaue them til it rot, then thruſt out the matter, but leaue the rootes; they wil come out as hee healeth, annoynting the Mangie places with Oyle Oliue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Lampe Oyle, fine powder of brimſtone, of blacke Sope, Tarre, barrow Hogges-greace, and the Sutte of a chimnie; of each alike, and then mixe them altogether, and annoynt the place therewith ſo hot as may be ſuffred, and it wil helpe him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the mangie of a dogge.</head>
               <p>Take Vinegar, Gunpowder, blacke Sope, Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, burnt Allum, and Verdigreace: boyle altogether with Honey and rubbe ouer the mangie place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the ſtrangle-halt.</head>
               <p>Take vp the Maſter-veine aboue the knee, and vnderneath the ſame Veine lyeth a ſtring, cutte it away: then cutte him below the noſtrils, and take away two ſtrings, and then annoynt him with but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Mares Evill.</head>
               <p>Take Milke, Oate-meale, Mallowes, Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Horehound, and Smallage, wring theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your hands, and boyle them together till they bee ſoft, and lay it to the griefe, which will bring it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10523:26"/>to a head: then you muſt lance it; then take Red Lead, burnt Allum, and Roſen, beate theſe to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and caſt upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To take away the bones, Knobbe, or Ringbone.</head>
               <p>Take a pound of ſtrong Lée, and Sope, a quarter of
<hi>Vitriall Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> i. oz. of
<hi>Salarmoniacke,</hi> as much of Roch Allum, and boyle them together till they are thicke, and ſo vſe it for an Oyntment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gypſiacum</hi> the ſtrongeſt kind, lay it to with Cotten thrée or foure times, will take it away. This is good alſo for a ſplint: and though it bee a Thiſtula in the Crowne it will ſinke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Powle-evill; which commeth of a bruiſe behind the Eares.</head>
               <p>Take a hot Iron, but firſt take vp the haire all the whole compaſſe; then ſearch it with a hot Iron, and then take
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Leade and blacke Sope, and mingle them with water, and make it thicke, and anoint him therewith till it bee whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To make water for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a quart of water, halfe a pound of Roach Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, iiii, d. worth of Mercury, a quarter of a pound of verdigreace: and when you ſée the horſe curbe his head, waſh him with this water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Lay a Plaiſter of Hogges greace on, to ripen
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> place, and when it is rive, launce it, and thruſt through a hot Iron, if it bee very deepe, and keepe it open wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> tents made of Spunge, and dippe it in Hogges greace: vſe this for foure dayes, then take Turepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and the yolkes of Egges and Saffron and mingle<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10523:27"/>them together, and dippe your tents of Spung therein, and bee ſure they goe to the bottome, and Plaiſter it with Hogges greace: and this will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Canker.</head>
               <p>You muſt take out his tongue, and let him blood in fiue or ſix places; and like wiſe on his vpper lippe that hee may bléede well, and all berubbe his tongue and lippes with ſalt, then the next day waſh his tongue and lippes with vineger, and rubbe it againe with Salt, and give him warme drinke and new Béere a day or two.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a colt-Evill.</head>
               <p>Take the iuice of Hemlocke, and waſh his yard and rods therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take beane flowre, vinegar, and <hi>Bolarmoniacke,</hi> and worke theſe together, and lay it to the codde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>You may waſh his ſhedde with warme vinegar, and draw forth his yard, and waſh it alſo: then ride him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water: let him ſwimme, and there toſſe ond turne him: vſe this two or thrée weekes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the coying.</head>
               <p>If he halt, pull off his ſhooe and open the place prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Knife, and powre in Turpentine, War, and Sheepes ſuet, being molten together: then cloſe it vp, and ſet on the ſhooe againe: let him reſt, and come in no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>et ground.</p>
               <p>Some doe vſe to burne the hole with a hot Iron, when they haue puld out the Naile; and ſome doe<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10523:27"/>powre in boiled butter in the hole once a day, and it hath cured it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take a handfull of nettles, of blacke ſope, of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, of each of them a ſpooneful, and three times ſo much Boares greace or Bacon greace; then ſtampe them wel together, and ſtoppe the Sore therewith, and it wil not rot any further, but heale, although you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour him.</p>
               <p>Some doe ſtoppe vp the hole when they draw forth the naile, with tallow and horſe-dung, and then ſet on the Shooe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Cordes.</head>
               <p>The cure is to flit it, and with a Bucks horne to take it vp, and tye it in two places, and cut it away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Muſtard, and Aquavity, and Sallet Oyle, and boyle them on the coales, and make a Plaſter, and hind it hot to the place. It is good alſo for any ſtraine, ſo it be new done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the Grounds of Ale, and being made warme, bathe his Legges therewith, and wiſpe him with a Hay rope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take ſmallage, and an hearb called Oxeye, and ſome Sheepes ſuet, choppe them altogether, and boyle it in mans vrine, and bathe the place therewith, and wet a Hay-hand in it, and rowle vp the legge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10523:28"/>
                  <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Curbs.</head>
               <p>Fret his Legges with thy hand, and then take red Colewort leaues, and Barrage, and bray them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and lay it thereto fiue dayes.</p>
               <p>Seethe a pound of blacke Sope in a quart of ſtrong Ale, til it looke like Tarre, and anoint the Sinewes therewith, and it wil ſupple them, and bring them to the right courſe. It is good for a man, if hee bee ſtiffe in the Ioynts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Enterfeeting.</head>
               <p>Hee may bee much holpen by ſhooing with a ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Smith: But if the Skinne bee off, take May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butter, with a quantity of yellow Roſen, as much Naruel; then fry them together in a Panne, and let it ſtand til it bee cold, and put it in a Potte, and put to it a little new Cow dung, and make Plaſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and binde it to the place. This wil heale alſo the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pricke of a Naile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Narvell galled.</head>
               <p>Take Sut of a Chimnie, and Yeeſt mixed together, and Plaſter it on: but ſhift it once a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take nettle ſéeds, &amp; mixe them with Sallet oyle and anoint the ſore, or chafe it therewith.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h him with warme water, and then anoint the place with Greace and Salt mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:10523:28"/>Take hearbe bittony, brimſt one in powder of
<hi>Elibory,</hi> pitch, and old greace, and ſtampe them together: and when you haue waſhed them with Chamber-lée, anoint him with this medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>A water for a Galled backe, or any foule ſore.</head>
               <p>Take a pottle of veriuyce, thrée penny worth of greene Copris, and boyle it to the one halfe, or more, and waſh the Sore with that, and then fill the Sore with red Lead; and let it not bee dreſſed of three dayes: and then dreſſe him againe, as you ſhalſee cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a greene wound.</head>
               <p>Take white Wine and make it warme, and waſh the Wound therewith, then take Turpentine, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>p,</hi> and a little Waxe, and me it them together, being ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, continually til they are wel mixed, and then vſe it. If it bee a cut, Take Tow, and dip if therein, and fil the wound with it: If it bee a hole, make Tents for the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Hogges greace and Venice Turpentine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and melt them together: and if it bee a Cut, take Tow and dippe therein, and fil the wound therewith. If it be a hole make Tents, and dreſſe it therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a hot impoſtume in any outward part.</head>
               <p>Stampe Liverwort, and mix it in the Grounds of Ale Mallowes, and Hogges greace, being made hot, and lay it thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:10523:29"/>Bruiſe Lettice ſéedes, and Poppie ſéedes, and mixe them with Oyle of Red roſes, and plaiſter-wiſe lay it on the ſore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For a cold Impoſtume.</head>
               <p>Take the hearbe Baulme; ſtamped and mixed with Hogges greace, and Plaiſter-wiſe lay it to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Séethe white Mint in Wine or Ale, with Oyle or butter and lay it hot to the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To ripen any Impoſtume.</head>
               <p>Séeth Mallowes rootes, and Lilly rootes, and then bruiſe them, and put therto Hogges greace, and Lin ſéed meale: and Plaiſter wiſe lay it to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Rheume.</head>
               <p>Let him blood in the Veine vnder the Taſte, and rub his Gummes with Sage tyed to a ſtickes end, and giue him for a while, the tender Crops of blacke Bryers in his Prouender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For looſe Teeth.</head>
               <p>Pricke the Gummes with a Knife, and then rubbe them with Honey, Sage, and Salt, beaten together. The Sorrel Horſe is moſt ſubiect to this Diſeaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Feaver.</head>
               <p>Let him blood in the Thigh in the middle veine foure ſingers vnder his Tuell: or elſe, take the Veine in the Necks, and giue him a drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:10523:29"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Water and Honey, the iuyce of Purſelaine, Gumme Dragone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Frankinſence in powder, with a few of damaſke Roſes, and mixe them altogether and giue it him to drinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take of Germander foure ounces, of <hi>Gumdragonet,</hi> and of dried Roſes, of each one oz. beate them all in fine powder, and put them in a quart of Good Ale, adding thereto Oyle of Oliue foure oz. of Honey as much: and giue it the horſe luke warme to drinke.</p>
               <p>If hee draweth his breath ſhort, and ſigheth with all let him blood in the Necke: and then take a pint of Wine, with <hi>di</hi> oz. of Sallet Oyle, and mixe therewith Frankinſence: and with the iii. part of the iuyce of Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, give it him to drink.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Fronce or Fronts.</head>
               <p>You muſt cut or burne them out: then waſh them with Beere and Salt, or Ale and Salt, and ſo they goe away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Gigges or Flappes.</head>
               <p>Gigges or Flappes, are Pimples, or Teats in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides of the mouth: you muſt cure them as you cure the Camery or Fronce; either wil helpe him.</p>
               <p>It is good to pull out the Horſes Tongue very often for feare of bréeding any Bliſters or Blaines, vnder his Tongue, or for feare of Hay-ſeed, which wil breede to ſome of thoſe diſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Gorge, or to bring Haire againe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:10523:30"/>Seare him with a hot Iron a handfull aboue the knée<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then rope him round about with a ſoft Rope of Hay, and powre on cold water, and let it remaine a night and a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To bring Haire againe.</head>
               <p>Take the dung of Goates, ſome Honey, and Allum, the blood of a Hogge: mixe them together, and heate them til they are ready to boyle, and being hot, rubbe the place therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take the ſoot of a Cauldron, mixed with Honey and Oyle and anoint the place therewith.</p>
               <p>Take greene walnut ſhels, and burne them to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and mixe them with honey, Oyle, and Wine, and anoint them therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For Gravelling.</head>
               <p>Thou ſhalt take off his Shooes, and pare out all the Gravell cleane (for if you leave any Grauell it wil breede to a ſoreneſſe called a Quitterbone,) then muſt you ſtuffe him with Turpentine and Hogges greace melted together, and dip in Tow or Flax, then clap on the thooe, and keepe it ſtopped, and ſhift it euery day til it bee whole, and let him come to no wet: If you ſtoppe it not vp well, it wil riſe aboue the hoofe: then you ſhall haue more buſineſſe, and put your horſe to more paine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the molt-long.</head>
               <p>It is an ill ſoreneſſe aboue the Hoofe, which wil bréed out in Knobs and bunches, with a watry humour.</p>
               <p>If it be in Summer, take blacke ſnayles, and burre rootes, and beate them together, lay it<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10523:30"/>thereto.</p>
               <p>If it bee in Winter, take the ſcraping of the bottome of the ſhagges of the Burre rootes, and put to it a handfull of the inner barke of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and beate them together, and plaiſter-wiſe lay it to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take Garlicke, Pepper, and honey, and ſtampe them together, and anoint his Tongue therewith, and thereof lay ſome to his Paſterns.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To ſtop a Laske of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>Take Beane flowre, and <hi>Bolearmoniacke,</hi> of each a quart: mingle theſe together in a quart of Red Wine, and giue it him luke-warm: let him reſt and kéep warm let him drinke no cold water, but luke-warme: and put in Beane flowre, and let him drinke but once a day, and not ouer-much, for the ſpace of three or foure dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>ob.</hi> of Allum, beaten in fine powder, and
<hi>Bolearmoniacke,</hi> beaten ſmall: and a quart of good milke: mingle them together til the milke bee of a curd, and giue it him to drinke, and diet him as afore ſaid: and this will ſtoppe him. <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Vines.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>remonic,</hi> honey, and violet leaues; ſtampe them together, and ſlit the ſinnew vnderneath the eare and lay a Plaſter thereto thrée dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Canker in the Noſe or Mouth.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:10523:31"/>If you ſee the Canker hee of greate heate, and burning in the Sore with exceeding paine, you ſhall take the iuice of purſlaine, Lettice, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, or Night-wade, and waſh the fore with a fine clout, or ſpout it on with a ſquirt, and this will kil it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>Another for the ſame, moſt ſingular.</head>
               <p>Take H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y, Sage, and Rue, of each a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th them in drine and Water, to the third part of them: ſtraine them out and put in a little white Copris and Honey, and a quantity, and ſo waſh the place with it. (It is a ſingular thing to remooue the molles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>) which done, you ſhall make a water to heale it, as thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Take rib-wort, bitonie, and Daiſies, of each a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: then ſeeth them in Wine and Water, and waſh the ſore thrée or foure times a day.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, that chriſtall made in pouder, is ſpecially good to kill the canker.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For any ſwelling of a Horſe.</head>
               <p>Take hemlocke and ſtampe it, and mingle it with ſhéepes doung and vinegar, and make a playſter, and lay it to the ſwelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>To heale the wound in the Lampas.</head>
               <p>Take a ſawcerful of Honey, and 12. Pepper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornes, and bray them together, and temper them with vineger, and boile them a while, and then lay it on the wound thrée or foure dayes: and then let him blood in the Lampas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>For the Ring-bone mallender</head>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:10523:31"/>Take a paring of a chéeſe, and roſt it wel, and lay it to the mallender as hot as hee may ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>Or elſe chafe it wel til the blood follow, and anoint it thereon: chafe it with a hot Iron, ſo that it hold to the mallender: then take ten flowres of Gillyflowres, ſet well, and henne-mucke, and temper them wel together and lay it on.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:32"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the farrier's profession</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a farrier's tools</figDesc>
               </figure> 
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:32"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:10523:33"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of the veins of a horse</figDesc>
                  <head>I B</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>The 2 temple v</item>
                        <item>The 2 eye. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 forhead. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 pallet. v</item>
                        <item>The 2 necke. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 plate. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 fore ſhanke. ve</item>
                        <item>The 2 ſide. ve</item>
                        <item>The ſhanke. ve</item>
                        <item>The houfe. v</item>
                        <item>The hanch. ve</item>
                        <item>The taile. ve</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10523:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
